# Shakiba Davari

Google Scholar: https://bit.ly/sdavari\_scholar

Email: sdavari@vt.edu

Website: https://bit.ly/sdavari

Research Interest

Intelligent Augmented Reality (AR) Interface Design: My research interest lies in connecting my past research experience in applied machine learning (ML) and my current passion for AR interfaces. I am a 3D interaction/interface designer, focusing on intelligent AR interfaces. I concentrate on different aspects of detecting AR user's context and utilizing it to adapt their AR interface. Such context-aware interfaces mitigate the existing challenges of AR, such as real-world occlusion and social intrusiveness, while providing more reliable and efficient information access and interaction in AR.

### Education

PhD., Computer Science

Dissertation Topic: Intelligent Augmented Reality Interfaces Virginia Tech 2018-May 2024

MSc., Computer Science

Specialization: Human Computer Interaction (Degree received) Virginia Tech 2018-2020

Specialization: Computational Perception and Robotics Georgia Tech 2017-2018

**BSc.**, Computer Engineering

Major: Computer Hardware (Degree received) Shahid Beheshti University, Iran 2010-2014

# Research Experience

Graduate Research Assistant Virginia Tech 2018 Aug-Present

Advisor: Doug A. Bowman

#### **Conceptual Framework Research:**

Applied a methodical approach based on a) consideration of end goals, features and challenges of AR, and b) in-depth review and analysis of existing AR interfaces, and context frameworks and taxonomies to:

- Propose a methodology for <u>classification of AR interfaces</u> and introduce Glanceable AR interfaces according to this classification [6].
- Propose a <u>taxonomy of the design dimensions</u> of AR interfaces [1].
- Propose a <u>taxonomy of context</u>, specifically tailored for capturing and inferring the intricacies and features crucial to effective intelligent AR interfaces [2, 4].
- Develop a <u>framework</u> for context-aware inference and adaptation tailored for the creation of intelligent AR interfaces [2, 4].

#### Socially Intelligent AR Interfaces:

• Designed and developed a <u>socially intelligent AR interface for HoloLens</u> devices, incorporating face and speech recognition to customize the content and display of the information based on

user's needs.

• Designed and conducted a user study on 36 participants to evaluate the <u>effect of AR interfaces</u> and <u>context-awareness</u> on the user experience and information access efficiency compared to mobile phones [3].

Tools: Python, OpenCV, DNNs, Flask web app development, Unity Game Engine, Photon, MRTK

#### Teamwork:

- Led a team of 10 graduate and undergraduate students to design an immersive VR experience using passive haptics and everyday proxy objects [5, 7].
- Designed and implemented numerous 3D Interaction techniques and communicated results in the winning team of the best 3D User Interface award at the IEEEVR conference for two consecutive years.
- Drill-AR: Facilitating drilling task at the Boeing Aircraft Company assembly line. Using Microsoft HoloLens, Drill-AR provided a simple AR UI that displays the drilling sequence on top of reality, speeding up the drilling process.
- OS-Level AR Interface: Designed and implemented a prototype of an AR Operating System Interface.

Research Scientist Intern

Adobe Inc.

2022 May-Aug

#### **Intelligent AR Interfaces for Document Navigation:**

- Designed and developed <u>16 different AR interfaces</u> for navigation through a large number of documents on iOS devices.
- Designed and conducted a <u>preliminary survey</u> on 8 participants to explore the effectiveness of these AR interfaces in multiple contexts.
- Utilizing the findings from the survey and iteratively applying the design cycle, selected the most promising candidate interfaces and <u>implemented them for HoloLens devices</u>.
- Designed and conducted a <u>user study on 24 participants</u> to evaluate the effectiveness of two different AR content placement strategies on <u>document navigation in four contexts</u> using a HoloLens2 device.
- Currently, analyzing the quantitative and qualitative data and preparing the manuscript for publication [1].

Tools: Apple ARKit, Swift, Adobe Aero, Unity Game Engine, MRTK, JMP

Research Intern Microsoft Inc. 2021 May-Aug

#### Exploring the Benefits of Virtual Monitors for Low-vision Population:

- Designed and developed a new tool to leverage the potentials of <u>virtual monitors for assisting</u> low-vision users.
- Designed and conducted a <u>user study on 21 low vision participants</u>.
- Derived valuable <u>design suggestions</u> for enhancing the hardware and software aspects of virtual monitors tailored to the needs of the low vision population.

Tools: Unity Game Engine

<sup>\*</sup> PERCxR: Workshop on Perceptual and Cognitive Issues in xR

<sup>\*\*\*</sup> ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology

#### Investigating the Effect of Leveraging Human Actions in Autonomous Cars:

Designed and developed various <u>driving simulation scenarios</u> to gather driver data across diverse situations.

Tools: SimVista, SimCreator

#### **Exploring Automation of Construction Progress Monitoring Using UAVs:**

Investigated and developed various algorithms to automate the <u>flight path of Unmanned Aerial</u> <u>Vehicles</u> (UAVs) within dynamic construction sites, for efficient image capture **[8]**.

Tools: Python2, OpenCV, Pymunck

Researcher University of Toronto 2015-2016

#### **Exploring Automation of Construction Progress Monitoring Using UAVs:**

• Combined various <u>ML classification models</u> and developed a robust system to categorize construction site images into one of the five states indicative of the construction progress [9].

Tools: Python2, OpenCV

#### Online Assistive Technology Rating System for Caregivers:

Automated web crawl and data extraction of target websites.

Tools: Selenium, Apache Nutch

Undergraduate Intern ZIEP Technical Company, Isfahan, Iran 2013 Aug.-Jun.

Advanced programming projects

Tools: C++ and C# Programming

# **Teaching Experience**

Graduate Teaching Assistant	Virginia Tech	2018 Aug-Present

#### **Department of Computer Science**

z cpan amont of compared concinct	
Introduction to Artificial Intelligence	Fall 2022
• Introduction to Human-Computer Interaction and Usability Engineering	ng Spring 2021
Introduction to Artificial Intelligence	Fall 2020
Professionalism in Computing	Summer 2020
Professionalism in Computing	Spring 2020
Introduction to Artificial Intelligence	Fall 2018

#### Instructor Shakhes Institute, Isfahan, Iran 2010-2012

Advanced programming workshops: C++, Python, VHDL, Verilog, C#

<sup>\*</sup> PERCxR: Workshop on Perceptual and Cognitive Issues in xR

- C++ programming
- RoboCup workshops

### **Honors & Awards**

• Invited Talk: "Context Aware Inference and Adaptation in Intelligent AR Interfaces"

PERCxR\* @ISMAR\*\* 2022

Best 3DUI Award

**IEEEVR 2020 & IEEEVR 2021** 

Departmental Service Award

CS Department @Virginia Tech 2020

• Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing Scholarship

Virginia Tech 2022

Virginia Tech 2021

Inclusion, Diversity, and Accessibility Scholarship

**IEEEVR 2022** 

ACM Capital Region Celebration of Women in Computing Scholarship

Virginia Tech 2020

• Tapia Celebration of Diversity in Computing Scholarship

**Tapia Foundation 2020** 

Virginia Tech 2019

Georgia Tech-2017

Selected Exceptionally Talented Student in the Department of Engineering

SBU, Iran 2010-2014

• Fellowship in support of preparation for Iran's National University Entrance Exam

Ghalamchi Foundation, Iran 2006-2010

Ranked 1st in Nationwide Programming Exam

Nationwide Sama High School, Iran 2009

Ranked 3rd in Nationwide Math Exam

Nationwide Sama High School, Iran 2008

Fellowship in Support of High School Education

Sama private High School, Iran 2006-2010

### **Service Activities**

Poster Chair

**ACM Spatial User Interaction (SUI) 2024** 

Reviewer

CHI 2021 & 2023

**IEEEVR 2021 & 2022** 

<sup>\*</sup> PERCxR: Workshop on Perceptual and Cognitive Issues in xR

UIST\*\*\* 2022 AutomativeUI 2020

President

Virginia Tech Graduate Student Council 2020

• Vice President

Virginia Tech Graduate Student Council 2019 Iranian Society at Virginia Tech 2018 to 2021

Mentoring and Advising

Danny Stover 2022-2023 Alexander Giovanelli 2021-2022 Daniel Manesh 2021-2022

• Judge, System Software and Intelligent Systems

Virginia State Science and Engineering Fair 2020 Virginia State Science and Engineering Fair 2022

Member, The Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)

2019-Present

• Member, ACM's Council on Women in Computing

2019-Present

Member, IEEE Computer Society

2019-Present

Member, IEEE Young Professionals

2019-Present

• Member, Inspiring Women in Lifelong Leadership (I-WILL), Virginia Tech

2019-Present

Member, Iranian Women in Computing (IranWiC), USA

2019-Present

# **Publications**

#### Journal:

- [1] A taxonomy of AR design dimensions, and exploring the effect of AR content placement on document navigation, S. Davari, S. Petrangili, J. Hofswell, DA Bowman (In-preparation for ISMAR 2024)
- [2] <u>Intelligent AR: A Taxonomy of Context and a Design Framework, S. Davari, DA. Bowman (Inpreparation for ISMAR 2024)</u>
- [3] <u>Automated computer vision-based detection of components of under-construction indoor partitions,</u> H. Hamledari, B. McCabe, <u>S. Davari</u>, Automation in Construction 2017, Vol 74, pp. 78-94

<sup>\*</sup> PERCxR: Workshop on Perceptual and Cognitive Issues in xR

<sup>\*\*\*</sup> ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology

[4] <u>Automated Schedule and Progress Updating of IFC-Based 4D BIMs</u>, H. Hamledari, B. McCabe, <u>S. Davari</u>, A. Shahi, Journal of Computing in Civil Engineering 2017, Vol 31, Issue 4. pp. 04017012:1-16

#### Conference:

- [5] <u>Validating the Benefits of Glanceable and Context-Aware Augmented Reality for Everyday</u>
  <u>Information Access Tasks, S. Davari</u>, F. Lu, and DA. Bowman, IEEEVR 2022, New Zealand, pp. 436-444
- [6] <u>Exploration of Techniques for Rapid Activation of Glanceable Information in Head-Worn Augmented Reality,</u> F. Lu, <u>S. Davari</u>, and DA. Bowman, in the ACM Symposium on Spatial User Interaction (SUI) 2021, 11 pages
- [7] <u>Glanceable AR: Evaluating Information Access Methods for Head-Worn Augmented Reality,</u> F. Lu, <u>S. Davari</u>, L. Lisle, Y. Li and DA. Bowman, IEEEVR 2020, Atlanta, GA, USA. pp. 930-938
- [8] <u>UAV Mission Planning Using Swarm Intelligence and 4D BIMs in Support of Vision-based Construction Progress Monitoring and As-Built Modeling</u>, H. Hamledari, <u>S. Davari</u>, O. Sajedi, P. Zangeneh, B. McCabe, M. Fischer, Construction Research Congress 2018, USA, pp. 43-53
- [9] <u>UAV-Enabled Site-to-BIM Automation: Aerial Robotic and Computer Vision-based Development of As-Built/As-is BIMs and Quality Control</u>, H. Hamledari, <u>S. Davari</u>, E. Azar, B. McCabe, F. Flager, M. Fischer, Construction Research Congress 2018, Louisiana, USA, pp. 336-346
- [10] <u>Evaluation of computer vision-and 4D BIM-based construction progress tracking on a UAV platform</u>, H. Hamledari, B. McCabe, <u>S. Davari</u>, A Shahi, ER Azar, F Flager, Proc., 6TH CSCE/ASCE/CRC International Construction Specialty Conference 2017, Vancouver, Canada, pp. CON106:1-10

#### Other (Workshop, Demo papers):

- [11] [DC] Context-Aware Inference and Adaptation in AR, S. Davari, IEEEVR 2022, New Zealand, pp. 938-939
- [12] <u>Clean the Ocean: An Immersive VR Experience Proposing New Modifications to Go-Go and WiM Techniques</u>, L. Lisle, F. Lu, <u>S. Davari</u>, I. A. Tahmid, A. Giovannelli, C. Ilo, L. Pavanatto, L. Zhang, L. Schlueter, DA. Bowman, IEEEVR 2022, Christchurch, New Zealand [<u>Winner of the Best 3DUI Award</u>]
- [13] Fantastic Voyage 2021: Using Interactive VR Storytelling to Explain Targeted COVID-19 Vaccine

  Delivery to Antigen-presenting Cells, L. Zhang, F. Lu, I. A. Tahmid, S. Davari, L. Lisle, N.

  Gutkowski, L. Schlueter, DA. Bowman, IEEEVR 2021, Lisbon, Portugal [Winner of the Best 3DUI

  Award]

<sup>\*</sup> PERCxR: Workshop on Perceptual and Cognitive Issues in xR

<sup>\*\*\*</sup> ACM Symposium on User Interface Software and Technology

- [14] <u>Integrating Everyday Proxy Objects in Multi-Sensory Virtual Reality Storytelling, S. Davari</u>, F. Lu, Y. Li, L. Zhang, L. Lisle, X. Feng, L. Blustein and DA. Bowman, Everyday Proxy Objects for Virtual Reality (EPO4VR) Workshop @ ACM CHI 2021, 4 pages
- [15] Occlusion Management Techniques for Everyday Glanceable AR Interfaces, S. Davari, F. Lu, and DA. Bowman, WEVR @ IEEEVR 2020, USA, pp. 324-330
- [16] <u>Get the job! An Immersive Simulation of Sensory Overload</u>, L. Pavanatto, F. Lu, <u>S. Davari</u>, E. Harris, A. Folino, S. Imamov, S. Chekuri, L. Blustein, WS. Lages, DA. Bowman, IEEEVR 2020, Atlanta, GA, USA. pp. 509-510
- [17] Save the Space Elevator: An Escape Room Scenario Involving Passive Haptics in Mixed Reality, S. Davari, Y. Li, L. Lisle, F. Lu, L. Zhang, L. Blustein, X. Feng, B. Gabaldon, M. Kwiatkowski, D. A. Bowman, IEEEVR 2019, Japan, pp. 1405-1406